<chapter xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Colors, Depth, Space (and Time?)</title>

    <section>
      <title>Image File Formats</title>
        <subsection>
          <title>Vector Formats</title>
          <p>
            Vector formats represent images as a series of drawing instructions. Becuase of this, they are infinitely scalable. This is well suited for iamges that can be defined geometrically, but not as well for real-world images.

            Common file type: SVG (Scalable Vector Graphics).
          </p>
        </subsection>

        <subsection>
          <title>Raster Formats</title>
          <p>
            Raster formats represent images as a grid of color values (pixels).
          </p>
          <p>
            Raster images can be uncompressed or compressed.
          </p>
          <p>
            Uncompressed formats contain color data for each pixel. These files are quite large. Common file types: BMP, TIFF, RAW
          </p>
          <p>
            Compressed formats use a compression algorithm to minimize file size. Some of these algorithms are lossless, while others are lossy.
          </p>
          <p>
            Lossless compression algorithms contain enough information to exactly recreate the original image. Common file types: PNG (Portable Network Graphics), GIF (Graphics Interchange Format)
          </p>
          <p>
            Lossy compression algorithms do not retain all the details of the original image. Common file type: JPEG (Joint Photographic Experts Group).
          </p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection>
          <title>NetPBM File Formats</title>
          <p>
            A family of uncompressed raster image file formats (<url href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Netpbm">more info</url>).
          </p>
          <p>
            In this class we will be using the <em>PPM</em> (Portable PixMap) format specifically. PPM files prespresent pixel data as RGB (Red, Green, Blue) triplets in either ASCII or binary. In ASCII based PPMs, all whitespace is equivalent. Here is a sample ASCII PPM file:
          </p>
          <cd>
            P3
            4 3
            255
            255 0 0  255 0 0  255 0 0  255 0 0
            0 255 0  0 255 0  0 255 0  0 255 0
            0 0 255  0 0 255  0 0 255  0 0 255
          </cd>
          <p>
            The first three lines make up the file header:
            <ul>
              <li><c>P3</c>: Type of PPM, 3-btye RGB, in ASCII (<c>P6</c> is RGB in binary).</li>
              <li><c>4 3</c>: Width x Height, in pixels.</li>
              <li><c>255</c>: Maximum value per color (will scale to 255 if not 255)</li>
            </ul>
          </p>
        </subsection>
    </section>
  </chapter>
